{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The completion of this project was celebrated with the first ticker-tape parade held in New York City. Originally planned as a lighthouse on the Suez Canal, this project was built on an exclave called Bedloe's Island and rests on steel infrastructure designed by Gustave Eiffel. A broken chain lies at the feet of this sculpture, whose title figure holds a tablet in her left arm. Designed by Frederic Bartholdi, for ten points, what is this colossal sculpture of a crowned woman holding a torch in New York Harbor?",
      "answer": [
        "Statue of Liberty",
        "Liberty Enlightening the World",
        "La Liberté éclairant le monde"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During these conflicts, Louis, Prince of Condé [[kaw-DAY]], launched a failed coup during the Surprise of Meaux [[MOH]]. The controversial Edict of January motivated a force led by the Duke of Guise [[GEES]] to perpetrate the Vassy Massacre, beginning these wars. The patron of the failed Fort Caroline mission in Floride [[floh-REED]], Gaspard de Coligny [[koh-lihn-YEE]], was assassinated during these wars in the St. Bartholomew's Day Massacre. The persecuted Huguenot minority fought the crown forces during, for ten points, what general period of sixteenth-century wars ended by the Edict of Nantes?",
      "answer": [
        "French Wars of Religion",
        "descriptive answers like Wars between the Protestants and Catholics in France before mentioned",
        "Huguenots in place of Protestants in descriptive answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This devastating event was the subject of the treatise Loimologia [[loy-moh-LOH- gee-ah]] which was written by a physician who personally witnessed this event, Nathaniel Hodges. In an attempt to stop this event, the village of Eyam lost over 200 people after collectively participating in an early instance of quarantining for disease control. Due to this event, the royal capital moved to the cities of Salisbury and Oxford after the wealthy, led by King Charles II, fled London. For ten points, name this 17th century epidemic which ravaged England, a blight caused by Yersinia pestis.",
      "answer": [
        "The Great Plague",
        "the Great Plague of London",
        "the Plague of 1665",
        "Plague of 1666"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A holder of the position who resided at Quispiguanca [[kwees-pee-GWAHN-kah]] employed ethnic groups including the Cachis as yanakunas. A holder of this position who built the Sacsayhuaman [[sahk-say-HWAH-mahn]] legendarily turned stones into warriors to defend his city from the rival Chanka people. After Vincente de Valverde gave the last holder of this position a Bible, he threw it back in his face. That holder of this position ordered a room to be filled with gold after being captured at the Battle of Cajamarca [[kah- hah-MAHR-kah]]. For ten points, name this royal position whose last holder was Atahualpa [[ah-tah-HWAHL-pah]].",
      "answer": [
        "Incan Emperor or Sapa Inca",
        "answers indicating the ruler of the Incan Empire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This activist traveled with Henry Morgenthau Jr.'s wife to the Westmoreland Homesteads in Pennsylvania, after which residents renamed the area after the last syllables of her name. 165 homes for unemployed local miners and farmers were constructed with assistance from this woman in Arthurdale, West Virginia. This woman resigned from the DAR after it refused to allow Marian Anderson to play Constitution Hall, and this diplomat served as the first Chair of the UN Commission on Human Rights. For ten points, name this longest-serving First Lady, the wife of FDR.",
      "answer": [
        "Eleanor Roosevelt",
        "Anna Eleanor Roosevelt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, French GIGN commandos assisted in the liberation of a mosque in 1979 after a two-week siege. The Italian adventurer Ludovico di Varthema wrote one of the first Western accounts of travel in this city, whose metro system only operates for seven days per year. This city demolished its Ottoman Ajyad Fortress in 2002 to make way for the Towers of the House hotel complex, which has the largest clock face in the world. The Masjid al-Haram and the Kaaba are located in, for ten points, what holiest city of Islam?",
      "answer": "Mecca"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these buildings at Gharni built by King Tiridates [[tee-ree-DAH-tees]] of Armenia was converted into a summer residence by Arsacid Queen Khosrovidukht [[kohs- roh-VEE-dookt]]. To celebrate the victory at Chaeronea [[kay-roh-NEH-ah]], Athenian sculptor Leochares [[leh-oh-KAH-rehs]] was commissioned with building one of these structures known as Philippeion. The \"Sacred Way\" connected the city of Samos to one of these locales known as the Heraion. Artemis is the dedicatee of an \"Ancient Wonder of the World\" in Ephesus which is, for ten points, what type of religiously significant structure?",
      "answer": [
        "Greek Temples",
        "Sanctuaries",
        "equivalents 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the film X-Men: Days of Future Past, this person becomes head of the anti-mutant movement after Mystique assassinates Bolivar Trask. In another film, this man presents Forrest Gump the U.S. table tennis tournament medal. In an episode of Futurama, this person presents a soldier with the Purple Heart for handing him the television remote while on the couch with his vice president, the “Headless Body of Spiro Agnew.” For ten points, name this 37th president of the United States who was involved in the Watergate Scandal.",
      "answer": "Richard Nixon or Richard Milhous Nixon"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this conflict, two girls who were allegedly asked for instructions on making gunpowder were captured at Wethersfield. During a pursuit of the Manisses in this conflict, several villages were burned by forces under Colonel John Endicott. Disputes over the fur trade were a cause of this conflict instigated by the murder of John Stone. Lasting from 1636 to 1638, this conflict took place in territory adjacent to the Connecticut River. For ten points, name this war between New Englanders and a namesake tribe ended by the Treaty of Hartford.",
      "answer": "Pequot War"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1962, a player of this instrument and his orchestra toured the Soviet Union as part of a cultural exchange program after the Cuban Missile Crisis. A player of this instrument, who led concerts at Guadalcanal while in the Navy, popularized Cole Porter’s \"Begin the Beguine\" [[beh-GEEN]] and added Billie Holiday to his band in 1938. Another player of this instrument led his band in a rendition of Louis Prima's \"Sing Sing Sing\" at a monumental 1938 concert at Carnegie Hall. For ten points, name this woodwind instrument played by Artie Shaw and Benny Goodman.",
      "answer": "Clarinet 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The perpetrator of this event determined to defend himself personally in court, against his lawyer's recommendation, and later recited his poem \"I am Going to the Lordy\" at the gallows. The victim of this event was treated by Alexander Graham Bell, who devised a metal detector to find the bullet lodged in the body of this event’s victim. This event occurred at the Baltimore and Potomac Railroad Station in Washington, D.C. and was perpetrated by Charles Guiteau [[ghee-TOH]]. For ten points, identify this event that led to Chester A. Arthur ascending to the presidency.",
        "answer": [
          "Assassination of James Abram Garfield",
          "synonyms for Assassination such as Murder"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Garfield’s assassination was instrumental in the passage of this piece of legislation which reformed the process of bureaucratic office appointment and effectively ended the spoils system.",
        "answer": "Pendleton Civil Service Reform Act"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country's first free elections were held in 1960, but the Coup of May 16th deposed its Second Republic and reversed the reforms of the April Revolution. This country's Yushin Constitution was signed shortly before an Olympic ceremony in which a number of doves were burnt alive. That tragedy in this country occurred in 1988, nine years after Nobel Prize laureate Kim Dae-Jung was elected its president. A northern neighbor invaded, for ten points, what Asian nation, leading to a 1950s war?",
        "answer": [
          "South Korea or Republic Of Korea",
          "or Daehan Minguk",
          "or Namhanguk",
          "do not",
          "or"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A South Korean dictator who promulgated the Yushin Constitution had this family name, shared by his daughter, another president who was impeached in 2017.",
        "answer": "Park"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's scholarly father, James, wrote an anti-Hindu historiography chronicling English colonialism in The History of British India. With Henry Hunt, this man was the first member of Parliament to openly call for women's suffrage in England, and this man wrote The Subjection of Women after conversations with his wife, Harriet Taylor. The teachings of Jeremy Bentham inspired, for ten points, what philosopher and MP who wrote Utilitarianism?",
        "answer": "John Stuart Mill"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Stuart Mill called for the eradication of poverty through what kind of tax, which was implemented in the U.S. through the 16th amendment?",
        "answer": "Income Tax 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One holder of this federal cabinet position was forced to resign from an earlier state position after serving as the second in a duel that led to Button Gwinnett’s death. That man, Joseph Habersham, succeeded a holder of this position who was a strong supporter of Britain during the War of 1812 and an organizer of the Hartford Convention. Timothy Pickering and Samuel Osgood held this position which, prior to independence, was held by Ben Franklin. For ten points, name this position that oversees the USPS.",
        "answer": [
          "United States Postmaster General",
          "PMG"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A brief rival business of the U.S. Postal Service was what express mail service that used relay teams to reduce the time to get messages from coast to coast to ten days?",
        "answer": [
          "Pony Express",
          "Central Overland California and Pike's Peak Express Company"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Due to the details of this event being supposedly known by Father Henry Garnet, this event became known as the Jesuit Treason. Francis Tresham was suspected of sending a letter to William Parker that eventually revealed the details of this event. Lord Monteagle investigated this event, which resulted in a last stand at Holbeche House. For ten points, what event was conspired by Sir Everard Digby, Robert Catesby, and Guy Fawkes to assassinate King James I of England?",
        "answer": [
          "Gunpowder Plot or Gunpowder Treason Plot",
          "Jesuit Treason before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Guy Fawkes Night is celebrated on what date, commemorated by the song lyric, \"Remember, remember [this date]?\"",
        "answer": [
          "November 5th",
          "\"Remember, Remember, the Fifth of November\""
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a 2017 song, this artist sampled Fox News anchors Eric Bolling, Kimberly Guilfoyle and Geraldo Rivera claiming his music does more damage to black youths than the institution of racism. In reference to General Sherman's Special Field Orders, this rapper says he needs \"forty acres and mule\" not a \"forty ounce and a pit bull\" on the song \"For Sale (Interlude).\" During the procession on the 20th anniversary of the Million Man March for racial equality, this artist's song \"Alright\" was used as an anthem. A Pulitzer Prize for Music was awarded to, for ten points, what Compton-born rapper of To Pimp a Butterfly?",
        "answer": [
          "Kendrick Lamar",
          "either underlined portion",
          "or Kendrick Lamar Duckworth",
          "K.Dot",
          "Kung Fu Kenny"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which U.S. president met with Kendrick Lamar at the oval office after citing \"How Much a Dollar Cost\" as his favorite song of the year?",
        "answer": "Barack Obama or Barack \"Barry\" Hussein Obama II 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One commander at this battle, Ariabignes [[ah-ree-ah-BIG-nees]], was allegedly speared to death by Socles and Ameinias [[ah-MEY-nee-ahss]]. A deceptive message lured one side to the site of this battle, in which the playwright of Prometheus Bound, Aeschylus [[EH-skih-luss]], participated. Prior to this battle, one side lost over one-third of its ships in a storm near Magnesia. Eurybiades [[yoo-rih-BYE-ah-dees]] assisted the winning commander at this 480 BCE battle fought in a set of namesake straits. For ten points, name this victory for Themistocles over the navy of Xerxes.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Salamis",
          "Naumachía tês Salamînos"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Salamis can be found in this modern-day Greek administrative region, a peninsula which contains Athens and was divided into demoi during the reforms of Cleisthenes [[KLY- stheh-nees]].",
        "answer": [
          "Attica",
          "Periféria Attikis",
          "Attic Peninsula"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A play by this author opens with a Catholic martyr quelling rioters from Lombardy on Evil May Day. Thomas Nashe may have co-written the Temple Garden scene with this author in a trilogy of plays in which nobles pluck red or white roses to support either the Duke of Somerset or Richard Plantagenet. This author of Sir Thomas More wrote a play whose protagonist describes himself as \"determined to prove a villain\" in a speech opening \"Now is the winter of our discontent.\" For ten points, name this playwright of histories including Henry VI and Richard III.",
        "answer": "William Shakespeare"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry VI, Part One was possibly a collaboration between Shakespeare and this other playwright, whose own history-inspired plays include Edward the Second and Tamburlaine.",
        "answer": "Christopher Marlowe"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "New Deal",
      "prompt": "Concerning the New Deal, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who put forth the program.",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "System of universal retirement pensions established during it.",
          "answer": "Social Security"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. state which names a \"Valley Authority\" that managed a series of hydroelectric dams.",
          "answer": [
            "Tennessee",
            "Tennessee Valley Authority"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Program for unmarried, unemployed young men which had them create public works of art and upkeep parks.",
          "answer": "CCC or Civilian Conservation Corps"
        },
        {
          "question": "Strategy used by the president to fill the judiciary branch with pro-New Deal judges.",
          "answer": "Court-packing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the early days of the New Deal which included the creation of a new bank holiday and passage of the Securities Act.",
          "answer": "The First Hundred Days"
        },
        {
          "question": "Initially pejorative term used to refer to agencies which used various acronyms like the FCC and NRA.",
          "answer": [
            "Alphabet Agencies",
            "Alphabet Soup"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Act passed which abandoned the harmful policy of Native American assimilation.",
          "answer": "Indian Reorganization Act 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Oliver Cromwell",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Seventeenth-century leader Oliver Cromwell, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Conflict which he and his Parliamentarians won over the Royalists, facilitating his rise to power.",
          "answer": "English Civil Wars"
        },
        {
          "question": "King who was finally defeated, deposed, and executed under his auspices in 1649.",
          "answer": "Charles I of England"
        },
        {
          "question": "Title he took while ruling the Commonwealth, essentially establishing himself as dictator.",
          "answer": "Lord Protector"
        },
        {
          "question": "1645 battle, the site of the final decisive defeat of Royalist forces.",
          "answer": "Battle of Naseby"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Leftover\" Parliament which preceded his rule and succeeded the Long Parliament.",
          "answer": "Rump Parliament"
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish city that his forces brutally sacked following a 1649 siege.",
          "answer": [
            "Drogheda ]",
            "Siege of Drogheda",
            "be lenient on pronunciation"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1653 John Lambert-authored document which outlined how the Commonwealth was to be ruled.",
          "answer": "Instrument of Government"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the effort to seize much of the Spanish Caribbean, leading to the capture of Jamaica.",
          "answer": "The Western Design 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Turkey",
      "prompt": "Who or what from the history of Turkey was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First president of the modern republic, who championed a secularist ideology?",
          "answer": "Mustafa Kemal Atatürk or Mustafa Kemal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose ambassador, Andrei Karlov, was assassinated in Turkey in 2016?",
          "answer": [
            "Russian Federation or Rossiya",
            "or Rossiyskaya Federatsiya"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country which underwent forcible population exchanges with Turkey of over 1.5 million people in the 1920s?",
          "answer": [
            "Greece or Hellenic Republic",
            "or Ellinikí Dimokratía"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "English translation of the Turkish phrase \"derin devlet\" referring to unelected interests that wield true power?",
          "answer": "Deep state"
        },
        {
          "question": "1920 treaty formally resolving Ottoman and Turkish participation in World War One?",
          "answer": "Treaty of Sèvres ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Weapon-based metaphor for the main principles of Turkish republican ideology?",
          "answer": "Six Arrows or Altı Ok"
        },
        {
          "question": "Militant wing of the MHP party involved in the assassination attempt on Pope John Paul II?",
          "answer": [
            "Grey Wolves or Bozkurtlar",
            "Idealist Hearths",
            "Ülkü Ocakları"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1922 standoff over control of the Dardanelles that nearly caused a war with the UK?",
          "answer": "Chanak Crisis or Çanakkale Krizi 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person asserted that aliens visiting the Earth would be comparable to Christopher Columbus’s arrival in the Americas. Five essays and five biographies of influential scientists were published by this thinker in a book titled On the Shoulders of Giants. (20 pts)",
        "This scientist’s final theory proposed that the universe is a “hologram.” Giving his name to a type of radiation that is emitted by black (10 pts)",
        "holes, for ten points, what British physicist’s works include A Brief History of Time and The Theory of Everything?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Stephen Hawking or Stephen William Hawking",
        "Hawking Radiation"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Now a National Park, this location contains the Red Shirt Table, named after a leader of the Ghost Dance Movement. Under the Mission 66 Plan, the Ben Reifel Visitor Center was built at this place, which was given to the Oglala in perpetuity in the later-broken Second Treaty of Fort (20 pts)",
        "Laramie. The \"Stronghold District\" in this area was seized during World War Two for use as a firing range. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this Sioux-populated National Park that contains the United States's largest undisturbed mixed-grass prairie."
      ],
      "answer": "Badlands National Park or Makȟóšiča"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a poem in this language, three cowardly brothers flee from a battle, one riding on his own lord's horse. That poem has been the subject of translation controversies of the word \"ofermode,\" meaning \"pride\" or \"arrogance.\" Historical (20 pts)",
        "texts in this language, including one that describes the sea as a \"whale-road,\" feature compound metaphors called \"kennings.\" A 1731 fire partially destroyed the Nowell Codex, which contains a poem in this language about a prince of the Geats. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this language of the poems \"The Battle of Maldon\" and Beowulf."
      ],
      "answer": "Old English"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An organization named for this body of water gave up nearly all of its land holdings for 300,000 pounds via the Deed of Surrender. Members of that organization named for this body of water were massacred by Cuthbert Grant at the Battle of Seven (20 pts)",
        "Oaks. This body of water's drainage basin, which was known as Rupert's Land, was awarded to a namesake company. This body of water takes its name from an explorer who captained the Half Moon. \"Point blankets\" were traded for furs (10 pts)",
        "by an organization named for, for ten points, what large Canadian body of water?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hudson Bay",
        "Hudson's Bay Company 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After his death, this man supposedly caused the inhabitants of the Kentish city of Strood to be born with tails for siding with the crown. This religious figure temporarily fled to mainland Europe to the court of Louis VII [[the Seventh]] (20 pts)",
        "following his dissent at the Constitutions of Clarendon. Henry II's possible utterance of the phrase \"Will no one rid me of this turbulent priest?\" was directed toward this man who was (10 pts)",
        "slain by knights led by Hugh de Morville. A 12th century assassination targeted, for ten points, what canonized archbishop of Canterbury whose gravesite became a pilgrimage destination?"
      ],
      "answer": "Thomas à Becket"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A numerically superior force under James Abercrombie failed to take this location, which was fortified with a lengthy series of abatis, or sharpened tree branches. This fort was originally built by the French and was known as Fort (20 pts)",
        "Carillon [[cah-ree-YOHN]]. Ethan Allen supposedly woke up the commander defending this location after he took it in a surprise attack with a small force of (10 pts)",
        "Green Mountain Boys. For ten points, identify this fort located near the south end of Lake Champlain in Northern New York."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Fort Ticonderoga",
        "Fort Carillon before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this industry, such as Monier Gondy, were the victims of increased crime in the aftermath of Hurricane Katrina. The inspiration for the play Waiting for Lefty was a 1934 strike of workers in this industry, a strike that was faced by Mayor Fiorello (20 pts)",
        "LaGuardia. A clothier from Chicago founded a private company in this industry called Checker. Medallion prices (10 pts)",
        "have decreased in this industry as a result of shared economy companies like Lyft and Uber. For ten points, name this industry, traditionally dominated by yellow automobiles."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Taxi industry",
        "Taxicab industry",
        "New York Taxi industry even though not all clues are from New York",
        "Checker Cab"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this group were selected to suppress the Coeur d'Alene [[koor dah-LEEN]] mining disputes of 1892 and 1899 to increase hostility. A man who served 28 years with this group, and named a giant sequoia after Booker T. Washington, was named Charles (20 pts)",
        "Young. This group was discriminated against by white residents in the Brownsville affair. Due to his work with a branch of this group called the 10th Cavalry Regiment, John Pershing (10 pts)",
        "earned the nickname \"Black Jack.\" For ten points, give this unofficial nickname of African-American regiments that often fought against Native Americans."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Buffalo Soldiers",
        "10th Cavalry Regiment before mentioned 2021-22 HS National History Bowl"
      ]
    }
  ]
}